Guide to the New-York Historical Society Library Department Records 1815-2018 NYHS-RG 21
New-York Historical Society
- Series VIII. Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC, a/k/a Print Room), 1940-2018 (bulk, 1970s-2013); 32.17 Linear feet
  - Subseries VIII.A. Curatorial & Administrative Files, 1950s-2015; 18 Linear feet in 40 boxes and two oversize folders
    - Wendy Shadwell Files (3 of 6 boxes), 1978-1994 (Offsite-box 215, Folder 1-16)
      Includes files concerning specific collections, including Bracklow, Long Island Fishermen, photographs, and the MTA collection (including documents related to the MTA's claims on the collection), and conservation matters.
    - Wendy Shadwell Files (4 of 6 boxes), 1969-1997 (Offsite-box 216, Folder 1-8)
      Includes files on acquisitions and correspondence with dealers (purchases, offers), including index cards with entries for acquisitions 1969-74. Also includes budget data (1989-1994) and a compiled list of Print Room staff (1917-80).
    - Wendy Shadwell Files (5 of 6 boxes), 1976-1993 (Offsite-box 217, Folder 1-11)
      Includes staff memos, both to general staff and to specific individuals, including the heads of the Library (Larry Sullivan, James Mooney) and the Museum (Holly Hotchner), and some correspondence.
    - Wendy Shadwell Files (6 of 6 boxes), 1984-1995 (Offsite-box 218, Folder 1-16)
      Includes correspondence regarding reference inquiries and various subject files (volunteer hour summary for fiscal year 1995, blank forms, "show & tell" presentations to school groups, and emergency/safety procedures).
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (1 of 16 boxes), 1989-1994 (Offsite-box 220, Folder 1-8)
      Includes correspondence concerning research requests, reproductions, and other architectural collections use.
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (2 of 16 boxes), 1994-1998 (Offsite-box 221, Folder 1-6)
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (3 of 16 boxes), 1991-1998 (Offsite-box 222, Folder 1-10)
      Includes files concerning grants, particularly for Cass Gilbert-related projects.
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (4 of 16 boxes), 1990-1996 (Offsite-box 223, Folder 1-17)
      Includes 14 folders concerning grants, primarily for conservation and general information. Also includes 2 plastic containers and a folder of 3" and 5" floppy disks; the labeling indicates these include various general work memos and exhibition matter.
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (5 of 16 boxes), 1991 (Offsite-box 224, Folder 1-16)
      Includes files concerning the exhibition McKim, Mead & White's New York.
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (6 of 16 boxes), 1991 (Offsite-box 225, Folder 1-19)
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (7 of 16 boxes), 1991 (Offsite-box 226, Folder 1-15)
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (8 of 16 boxes), 1991 (Offsite-box 227, Folder 1-3)
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (9 of 16 boxes), 1992 (Offsite-box 228, Folder 1-12)
      Includes files concerning the exhibition Building City Hall: Competition, Construction and Context [McComb].
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (10 of 16 boxes), 1992 (Offsite-box 229, Folder 1-22)
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (11 of 16 boxes), 1956, 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 230, Folder 1-25)
      Includes files concerning the exhibition Building City Hall: Competition, Construction and Context [McComb]. Includes the pamphlet "The Rehabilitation of City Hall" by Frederick H. Zurmuhlen (1956) with a ticket to the Rededication Ceremony of July 12, 1956.
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (12 of 16 boxes), 1994 (Offsite-box 231, Folder 1-15)
      Includes files concerning the exhibition The Grand American Avenue [Fifth Ave].
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (13 of 16 boxes), 1995-1996 (Offsite-box 232, Folder 1-7)
      Includes files concerning the exhibition In Cold Blood: Five Murders that Shocked New York.
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (14 of 16 boxes), 1997 (Offsite-box 233, Folder 1-14)
      Includes files concerning the exhibition Signs and Wonders: The Spectacular Lights of Times Square.
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (15 of 16 boxes), 1996-1997 (Offsite-box 234, Folder 1-8)
      Includes files concerning the exhibition Signs and Wonders: The Spectacular Lights of Times Square. Includes a pre-publication version of the book Signs and Wonders by Tama Starr & Edward Hayman.
    - Mary Beth Betts Files (16 of 16 boxes), 1995-1998 (Offsite-box 235, Folder 1-12)
      Includes files for exhibitions concerning food (proposed), Landmarks of New York, Kid City, George B. Post, and notes and other documents related to other exhibitions or proposed exhibitions.
    - Cataloging Worksheets (1 of 2 boxes), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 249, Folder 1-4)
      Includes worksheets for the McComb and Pollard architectural collections.
    - Cataloging Worksheets (2 of 2 boxes), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 250, Folder 1-46)
      Includes worksheets for the Davis and Cass Gilbert architectural collections.
    - Dale Neighbors Files (1 of 5 boxes), 1994-1997 (Offsite-box 236, Folder 1-7)
      Includes files concerning the 1995 Treasury of the Past ("Treasures") exhibition and plans for developing a "daybook"/calendar with photographs and other images from the collections.
    - Dale Neighbors Files (2 of 5 boxes), 1950s-1970s, 1994-1996 (Offsite-box 237, Folder 1-5)
      Includes files on the planning for a rotation of core New York City history-themed exhibitions, exhibition New York:Then and Now, and a set of clippings apparently from the 1950s-1970s and at least in part from a newspapers series "New York's Changing Scene."
    - Dale Neighbors Files (3 of 5 boxes), 1987-1998 (Offsite-box 238, Folder 1-15)
      Includes files on various exhibition proposals or possibilities (Bowery, Summer, Spanish-American War collection-based theme), as well as general exhibition matters; general correspondence (research inquiries, reproduction requests, loan requests, etc.); acquisition possibilities, including the Long Island Fisherman collection; administrative matters, including priorities, goals, activities, procedures; and facilities. Three oversize architectural plans from Richard Jansen were moved to a drawer.
    - Dale Neighbors Files. Oversize, 1990 (Drawer 12A-B7, Folder 18)
      Includes three plans from Richard Jansen, architect: Existing Furniture Layout, Third Floor; Third Floor Print Room: Proposed Furnishings; and Third Floor Print Room: Proposed Construction.
    - Dale Neighbors Files (4 of 5 boxes), 1988-1998 (Offsite-box 239, Folder 1-10)
      This box and the next includes Helena Zinkham's working files for her 1992 A Guide to Print, Photograph, Architectural and Ephemera Collections at N-YHS, a 1991 draft and the 1992 "Preliminary Edition" of the Guide, the working files for the 1998 publication of the Guide, mounted examples of publication format possibilities, and related correspondence. Three oversize images of the book's proposed covers were moved to an oversize box.
    - Dale Neighbors Files. Oversize, 1997 (Box OS-1, Folder 21)
      Includes three oversize images of the proposed covers for Helena Zinkham's 1997 guide to the Print Room collections.
    - Dale Neighbors Files (5 of 5 boxes), 1994-1998 (Offsite-box 240, Folder 1-4)
      Includes one folder of page proofs for Zinkham's 1998 Guide, an NEH grant request for preservation of negatives, and Durr collection photographs.
    - Pamela Dewey/Valerie Komor Files (1 of 4 boxes), 1999-2003 (Offsite-box 241, Folder 1-31)
      Includes files on exhibitions (principally small working files for Jesse Tarbox Beals and The Changing Face of Liberty); loan requests and returns; an agreement with Lehman Brothers concerning rights for material supplied by N-YHS for use on Morgan Stanley's HoloPro System; and acquisitions/donations and collection development policies.
    - Pamela Dewey/Valerie Komor Files (2 of 4 boxes), 1940s-2003 (Offsite-box 242, Folder 1-26)
      Includes collection descriptions, such as inventories, lists, surveys, counts, etc. The Landauer collection includes information about the transfer of objects to the museum and a folder of clippings and original magazines with articles dating from the 1940s-70s, among other documents. Also includes processing and project plans for cataloging and other description initiatives, including the monthly status reports for the Mellon-funded visual materials cataloging project.
    - Pamela Dewey/Valerie Komor Files (3 of 4 boxes), 1997-2003 (Offsite-box 243, Folder 1-33)
      Continues with files on collection description, including reports from the Mellon-funded studies on contemporary/contemporaneous collecting. Includes files concerning conservation, move of the Print Room to the 2nd floor, statistics, administrative matters (copyright, organization charts, and job descriptions), and a file related to Mary Beth Betts' presentation at a food/culinary historian program (1998).
    - Pamela Dewey/Valerie Komor Files (4 of 4 boxes), 1992-2004 (Offsite-box 244, Folder 1-34)
      Includes files on grant proposals (conservation, digitization, institutional archives, etc.), general correspondence, internal memos, a research folder on the history of the Dakota, and four color slides of abstract artworks by Pamela Lawton related to the World Trade Center (1998).
    - Holly Hinman Files. Photographers, 1993-1995, 2000-2004 (Offsite-box 245, Folder 1-53)
      Includes Hinman's files (A-Z) on photographers, likely in connection with potential acquisitions or exhibition. Many of the files have color slides, photographic prints, or digital media of the works; photographers with such original media include: Walter Chandoha, Jerry Dantzic, Stephanie Diamond, Morris, Engel, Gina Fuentes-Walker, Anders Goldfarb, Stephen Hoffman, Sheila Kove, G. David Marshall, Barbara Mensch, Elaine Norman, Christine Osinski, Gerald Panter, Orville Robertson, and Lynn Saville (other artists not named here commonly have print or other reproduction forms of their work). The box also holds a file of Hinman's notes for a presentation at N-YHS to an NYU class.
    - Negative Collections Surveys, 1948-2006 (Offsite-box 284, Folder 1-16)
      Includes files on various surveys of negative collections in the Print Room in the 1990s and early-mid 2000s. A small number of inventories, notes, correspondence, and other documents dating as early as 1948 related to negatives are in the files. Among this early material is a 1948 list of the Thomas H. Franklin Collection (Steamship Historical Society of America) glass plates deposited with N-YHS and notations concerning railroad photos in the George T. Bagoe collection.
    - Here is New York (30 folders), 2003-2012 (Offsite-box 275, Folder 1-30)
      Includes files primarily on the collection, with one folder regarding the 2007-2008 exhibition.
    - General Administrative Files, 1960-1999 (Offsite-box PPAC Collection Files 20)
      Includes acquisitions, correspondence, and loans.
    - General Administrative Files, 1980-1998 (Offsite-box PPAC Collection Files 21)
      Mainly correspondence about Architectural Collections.
  - Subseries VIII.B. Exhibition Files, 1940-2018; 12.5 Linear feet in 28 boxes and 1 oversize folder
    The subseries does not include the object and other research files underlying the exhibition and related Armory Show resource website. These research files were not accessioned into the institutional archive, but they are available to researchers directly from N-YHS's Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture. Contact printroom@nyhistory.org or use the on-line request form at https://www.nyhistory.org/library/reference-assistance. The website resource developed during the exhibition project can be accessed at https://www.nyhistory.org/exhibitions/armory-show-100.
    The subseries is arranged in chronological order by the year of an exhibition's opening year.
    The subseries includes sets of exhibition files that were maintained as standalone sets of files, or at least were found in that way during archival processing in 2016. The earliest files, from the 1940s and 1950s, appear to have been compiled at a later date by Wendy Shadwell and often include photographs of objects and the exhibition galleries. Later files often include photocopies of images of objects, but not of the galleries. Generally, the records are working files recording selections from the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (i.e., PPAC, or sometimes referred to as the Print Room) for museum and library exhibitions and the return of the items to the Print Room. Later files have the call slips for the selected documents. Many of the files have checklists, text, some research files, etc. The container list includes notes indicating those exhibitions that appear to have folders with more substantive or extensive documentation; the exhibition names used in the container list generally come from the original folder labels and likely do not match the actual exhibition titles precisely.
    A particularly rich set of documents in this subseries relates to the 2013 exhibition The Armory Show at 100. The subseries holds the files of exhibition curator Marilyn Kushner, which include checklists, loan documentation, design plans, publicity, and other documents.
    Subsequent to the major processing project in 2016, additional files of exhibitions curated or organized by the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture from 2016 and later were transferred to the archives and these are included in the subseries as well.
    - Exhibitions. 1940s (7 folders), 1940-1949 (Offsite-box 251, Folder 1-7)
      Includes photographs for Emma Thursby Memorial, Allied Artists, Jenny Lind, Our GIs in Seven Wars, American Presentation Silver, Audubon, Historic Hudson in Prints, News Artists to the American People, American & European Bookplates, American Quilts, and California Gold Rush.
    - Exhibitions. 1950s (2 folders), 1950, 1958 (Offsite-box 251, Folder 8-9)
      Includes Erie Canal and America in Daguerreotypes.
    - Exhibitions. 1960s (15 folders), 1960-1969 (Offsite-box 251, Folder 10-24)
      Includes, among others, Niagara Falls, New York's Crystal Palace, Transportation in New York, America in Allegory, Maps/Prints, Central Park, Advertising Posters, Summer in New York, Theatrical Posters.
    - Exhibitions. 1970s (12 folders), 1970-1974 (Offsite-box 252, Folder 1-12)
      Includes, among others, Eye on the City and Old New York in Early Photographs.
    - Exhibitions. 1970s (12 folders), 1974-1979 (Offsite-box 253, Folder 1-12)
      Includes Manhattan Now, Americans in Silhouette, Ain't I A Woman?, Landauer, Fashions & Facades, Feininger, Views of New York State, and 1939 World's Fair.
    - Exhibitions. 1980s (24 folders), 1981-1984 (Offsite-box 254, Folder 1-24)
      Includes, among others, Silhouettes by Edouart, George Washington in New York State, Birth of New York, A Bridge Opens to Brooklyn, Postcards, Her Voice Was Heard.
    - Exhibitions. 1980s (11 folders), 1984, 1986 (Offsite-box 255, Folder 1-11)
      Includes Chicago & New York: Architectural Interactions and Prized Portraits.
    - Exhibitions. 1980s (16 folders), 1984-1989 (Offsite-box 256, Folder 1-16)
      Includes, among others, Strong on Music, New York Bestiary, Government by Choice, Artistic Houses, George Washington, 1939 World's Fair.
    - Exhibitions. 1980s (6 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 257, Folder 1-6)
      Includes Treasures, Patronage (proposed; also known as Patrons, Collectors and Collections), Irving Browning, Burr McIntosh: Polite Society.
    - Exhibitions. 1990s (9 folders), 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 257, Folder 7-15)
      Includes, among others, Thomas Jefferson Bryan Prints, Archives Week, While They Fought: New York City Homefront During World War II.
    - Exhibitions. 1990s (18 folders), 1992-1994 (Offsite-box 258, Folder 1-18)
      Includes, among others, Strobridge Circus and Theater Posters (at Paine-Webber Gallery), Board Games, proposed gallery reinstallation of the permanent collections, Jefferson, Exhibition Lab.
    - Exhibitions. 1990s (12 folders), 1995-1997 (Offsite-box 259, Folder 1-12)
      Includes, among others, Treasury of the Past, Creating Fame, Age of Innocence, Audubon, World War II, Etchings from James Boyd Collection, Portraits of a New Yorker, Prints from the Reba and Dave Williams Collection.
    - Exhibitions. 1990s (10 folders), 1997-1999 (Offsite-box 260, Folder 1-10)
      Includes, among others, Signs & Wonders, Audubon, Feathers, Currier & Ives, George B. Post, Spanish-American War, Yadda Yadda Yadda.
    - Exhibitions. 1990s (10 folders), 1999 (Offsite-box 261, Folder 1-10)
      Includes, among others, Building History, Her Beautiful Face, Future Works, Genin the Hatter, Beals on Assignment
    - Exhibitions. 2000s (18 folders), 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 262, Folder 1-18)
      Includes Italians of New York, Strobridge Circus & Theater Posters, Jenny Lind, Up on the Roof, Against the Storm/Lighthouse Collection. See also Series VIII.C. Loans subseries; some exhibition folders appear to have been misfiled there including "Walkabout" and "Lady Liberty."
    - Exhibitions. 2000s (20 folders), 2001-2003 (Offsite-box 263, Folder 1-20)
      Includes, among others, Irwin Silver: Nightwalks, Flophouses, The British in New York Since 1770, Uncle Tom's Cabin, Flatiron, Jules Feiffer, Before Central Park.
    - Exhibitions. 2000s (15 folders), 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 264, Folder 1-15)
      Includes, among others, Magnum, Three Women Photographers, Petropolis, Home Sewn, Impressions of New York: Prints from N-YHS.
    - Exhibitions. 2000s (15 folders), 2004-2005 (Offsite-box 265, Folder 1-15)
      Includes, among others, From Abyssinian to Zion, If Elected, Tunnel Visions, Hamilton, Children at Risk, Beekman Coach, First Ladies, Hudson River.
    - Exhibitions. 2000s (19 folders), 2005-2007 (Offsite-box 266, Folder 1-19)
      Includes, among others, Slavery, Group Dynamics, Great Hall installation, John B. Snook, Sugar, and various mini-exhibitions.
    - Exhibitions. 2000s (19 folders), 2007-2008 (Offsite-box 267, Folder 1-19)
      Includes, among others, Carry Me Home, Tiffany/Clara Driscoll, Civil War Zouaves, Lafayette.
    - Exhibitions. 2000s (17 folders), 2007-2009 (Offsite-box 268, Folder 1-17)
      Includes, among others, Life's Pleasures/Ashcan Artists and Advertising/Ashcan, Grant & Lee, John Rogers, Landmarks of New York City.
    - Exhibitions. 2000s (8 folders), 2009 (Offsite-box 269, Folder 1-8)
      Includes only Nation at the Crossroads: New York Debates the Constitution (also referred to for short as Ratification).
    - Exhibitions. 2000s (10 folders), 2009, 2012 (Offsite-box 270, Folder 1-10)
      Includes mostly the 2009 exhibition Harlem: Photographs by Camilo Jose Vergara. Also includes one folder for the "Harlem 2" exhibition of Vergara's photographs in 2012. Also includes 2 folders for Lincoln in New York.
    - Exhibitions. 2010s (12 folders), 2010-2011 (Offsite-box 271, Folder 1-12)
      Includes, among others, World of Asher B. Durand, John Rogers, peter Marie Cabinets, Remembering 9/11.
    - Exhibitions. 2010s (5 folders), 2012-2013 (Offsite-box 272, Folder 1-5)
      Includes Freedom Now: Photographs by Platon, New York Buildings, Landmarks, Vergara Traveling Show re: Harlem, and Vergara Martin Luther King, Jr. photographs..
    - Exhibitions. 2010s. The Armory Show at 100 (1 of 4 boxes), 2013 (Offsite-box 276, Folder 1-15)
      This set of 4 boxes plus an oversize folder include the files of exhibition curator Marilyn Kushner. The files are arranged alphabetically by subject matter. This first box includes files on, among other topics, budgets, catalogue information, checklists, design (see also the oversize noted below), text, and representative wall text panels.
    - Exhibitions. 2010s. The Armory Show at 100 (2 of 4 boxes), 2013 (Offsite-box 277, Folder 1-11)
      Includes files on, among other subjects, development/funding, digital/website, education programs, and labels.
    - Exhibitions. 2010s. The Armory Show at 100 (3 of 4 boxes), 2013 (Offsite-box 278, Folder 1-12)
      Includes files on, among other subjects, loans, programs, publicity, and symposia, and a list of unlocated works (as of June 2010).
    - Exhibitions. 2010s. The Armory Show at 100 (4 of 4 boxes), 2013 (Offsite-box 279, Folder 1-15)
      Includes files on, among other subjects, travel and miscellaneous.
    - Exhibitions. 2010s. The Armory Show at 100. Oversize, 2013 (Box OS-1, Folder 22)
      Includes the floor plan, elevations, and other design plans for the exhibition.
    - Exhibitions. 2010s (13 folders), 2012-2014 (Offsite-box 273, Folder 1-13)
      Includes primarily Jewish Joint Distribution Committee (2014). Also includes Urban Views (2012), Stories in Sterling (2012), Farley Post Office (2013), Bill Cunningham Facades (2014), and Chinese Exclusion Act(2014).
    - Exhibitions. 2010s (9 folders), 2014, 2016 (Offsite-box 274, Folder 1-9)
      Includes Annie Leibovitz: Pilgrimage (2014) and Anti-Semitism (2016).
    - Exhibitions. 2010s (6 folders), 2016-2018 (Offsite-box 339, Folder 1-6)
      Includes "Larry Silver Photographs" (1 folder), "American Visionary: John F. Kennedy's Life & Times" (2 folders), "Rebel Spirits: Robert F. Kennedy and Martin Luther King, Jr." (1 folder), Kalinsky photographs of Muhammad Ali (1 folder), and "New York Through the Lens of George Kalinsky" (1 folder).
  - Subseries VIII.C. Loans, 1984-2016; 1.67 Linear feet
    The subseries includes loan requests, primarily for material outgoing to other institutions, but also includes some records of internal loans for exhibitions.
    The subseries is arranged chronologically. The material remains in its original folders and original order. Loans through 1995 or so are foldered together. After 1995, loans are foldered individually.
    - Loan Requests From Other Institutions, 1984-1998 (Offsite-box 280, Folder 1)
    - Loans Out at Other Institutions, 1985-1995 (Offsite-box 280, Folder 2)
    - Loans Rejected & Cancelled, 1991-1993 (Offsite-box 280, Folder 3)
    - Loans Out to Other N-YHS Departments, 1979-1996 (Offsite-box 280, Folder 4)
    - Loans Miscellaneous, 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 280, Folder 5)
    - Loans Returned (3 folders), 1984-1989 (Offsite-box 280, Folder 6-8)
    - Loans Returned, 1989-1995 (Offsite-box 281, Folder 1)
    - Individual Loan Files (15 folders), 1996-2000 (Offsite-box 281, Folder 2-16)
      Includes, among others, Parrish Art Museum, Stony Brook Museum, Yale, "Hair" (appears to be a proposed N-YHS exhibition), Brandywine River Museum, Nassau County Museum, Columbia University, MOMA, Baltimore Museum, Fraunces Tavern.
    - Individual Loan Files (18 folders), 2000-2002 (Offsite-box 282, Folder 1-18)
      Includes, among others, South Street Seaport, From Indian Princess to Lady Liberty (likely an N-YHS exhibition of a similar name), Stony Brook, Berry-Hill, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Walkabout (likely an N-YHS exhibition of a similar name), Museum of Sex.
    - Individual Loan Files (16 folders), 2003-2016 (Offsite-box 283, Folder 1-16)
      Includes, among others, Hirschl & Adler, Times Square exhibition, New York Botanical, Yeshiva University, Bard Graduate Center, Bronx Museum, New Orleans Museum of Art, Museum of the City of New York, Metropolitan Museum of Art, and the Roosevelt House Public Policy Institute at Hunter College
  - Subseries VIII.D. Collection Files, 1940-
    - Mixed Material Collections A-Ge (Offsite-box PPAC Collection Files 1)
      Album File (PR 02) [3 folders]
      Artistic Houses (PR 87) [1 folder]
      Bagoe Collection (No PR-Dispersed) [1 folder]
      Bannerman, Jane. Sketchbooks (PR 297) [1 folder]
      Benney, Robert L., Research Collection (PR 250) [1 folder]
      Ben Brown WWII Drawings (PR 274) [1 folder]
      Clark, Horace B. (PR 02-098) [1 folder]
      Certificate File (PR 014) [3 folders]